<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dangers of new discipline to the state and church discovered fit to be considered by them who seeke, as they tearme it, the reformation of the Church of England composed by a Trve Protestant, a loyall subject, a loving fellow member of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland ...</title>
            <author>True Protestant, a loyall subject, a loving fellow member of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland and Ireland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36405</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1376</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12773599</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12773599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93699</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36405)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93699)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 253:E155, no 24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dangers of new discipline to the state and church discovered fit to be considered by them who seeke, as they tearme it, the reformation of the Church of England composed by a Trve Protestant, a loyall subject, a loving fellow member of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland ...</title>
                  <author>True Protestant, a loyall subject, a loving fellow member of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland and Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. R.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Forms the first portion of a made-up tract, having general t.p. which reads: A discourse presented to those who seeke the reformation of the Church of England ... Printed for W. W. and I. B. 1642.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from BLC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England.</term>
               <term>Reformation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93699:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> DANGERS OF NEW DISCIPLINE, TO The STATE and CHURCH <hi>Diſcovered,</hi> FIT TO BE CONSIDERED By them who ſeeke (as they tearme it) the <hi>Reformation</hi> of the CHURCH of ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>COMPOSED BY A TRVE PROTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, a Loyall Subject, a Loving Fellow Member of the Common-Wealth of</hi> England, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>who dayly prayes for</hi> KING <hi>and</hi> PEOPLE <hi>and a Setled peace in all three</hi> KINGDOMES.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>W. R.</hi> ANN. DOM. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:93699:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93699:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> DISCOVRSE to them who ſeeke the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation (as they terme it) of the CHVRCH of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>BRETHREN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wiſdome of governours you muſt not blame, in that they, forecaſting the manifold, ſtrange, and dangerous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations, which are more then like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to follow, if your Diſcipline ſhould take place, have for that cauſe thought it hitherto a part of their duty, to withſtand your endeavours that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93699:3"/> way. The rather, for that they have ſeene already ſome ſmall beginnings of the fruits thereof in them, who concurring with you in Iudgment, about the neceſſity of that Diſcipline, have adventured with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more adoe to ſeparate themſelves from the reſt of the Church, and to put your ſpeculations in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. Theſe mens haſtyneſſe, the waryer ſort of you doe not Commend, you wiſh they had held themſelves longer in, and not ſo dangerouſly flowne abroad before the feathers of the cauſe had bene growne. Their errour with mercifull termes yee reprove, nameing them in great commiſeration of mind,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 22.</note> your <hi>poore Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They, on the contrary ſide, more bitterly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe you as their <hi>falſe Brethren,</hi> and againſt you they plead, ſaying, <hi>From your</hi> breſts it is that wee have <hi>ſucked thoſe things, which when yee delivered vnto us, ye termed that heavenly, ſincere, and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome milke of Gods word, howſoever yee now abhorre as poyſon, that, which the vertue thereof hath wrought and brought forth in us.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 55.13.</note> 
               <hi>Yee ſometimes our Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Guides, and familiars, with whom we have had moſt ſweet conſultations are now become our profeſsed Adverſaries, becauſe wee thinke the ſtatute-Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations in England to be no true Chriſtian-Churches, becauſe wee haue ſevered our ſelves from them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe without their leave or licence that are in civill Authority, wee have ſecretly framed our owne Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es according to the platforme of the word of God. For, of that point betweene you and us, there is no contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93699:3"/> Alas! what would you have us to doe? At ſuch time as yee were content to accept us in the number of your owne, your teachings wee heard, wee read your writings: and though wee would, yet able wee are not to forget with what zeale yee ever have profeſt, that in the</hi> Engliſh Congegations <hi>(for ſo many of them as bee ordered according unto their owne Lawes) the very publique ſervice of God is fraught, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing matter, with heaps of intolerable pollutions, and as concerning forme, borrowed from the ſhop of</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; <hi>hatefull both waies in the eyes of the most holy: the kind of their Government by</hi> Biſhops <hi>and</hi> Arch-Biſhops <hi>Antichriſtian; that Diſcipline which Chriſt hath eſſentially tyed, that is to ſay, ſo united unto his Church that wee cannot account it really to be his Church, which hath not in it the ſame Diſcipline, that very Diſcipline, no leſse there deſpiſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. againſt Docter Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</note> 
               <hi>then in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Throne of</hi> Antichriſt; <hi>all ſuch parts of the word of God, as doe any way concerne that Diſcipline, no leſſe vnſoundly taught and interpreted by all authorized Engliſh Paſtors, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Antichriſts factors themſelves; at Baptiſme Croſsing, at the lords ſupper kneeling; at both, a number of other the moſt notorious badges of</hi> Antichriſtian <hi>recogniſance vſuall. Being moved with theſe, and the like your effectuall diſcourſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto wee gave moſt attentive eare, till they entred even into our ſoules, and were as fire within our boſomes, wee thought wee might hereof bee bold to conclude, that ſith no ſuch</hi> Antichriſtian <hi>Synagogue may bee accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a true Church of Chriſt, yee by accuſing all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93699:4"/> ordered according to the Lawes of</hi> England, <hi>as</hi> Antichriſtian, <hi>did meane to condemne thoſe congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, as not being any of them worthy the true name of a Chriſtian Church; Yee tell us now, it is not your meaning. But what meant your often threatnings of them, who profeſſing themſelves the inhabitants of</hi> Mount Sion, <hi>were too loath to depart wholy, as they ſhould, out of</hi> Babilon; <hi>Whereat our hearts being fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully troubled, wee durſt not, wee durst not continue lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſo neere her confines, least her plagues might ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly overtake us, before wee did ceaſe to bee partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with her ſinnes: for ſo wee could not chuſe but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with greife that wee were, when they doing evill, wee, by our preſence in their Aſsemblies, ſeemed to like thereof, or, at leaſtwiſe not ſo earneſtly to diſlike as became men heartily zealous of Gods glory. For, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturing to erect the Diſcipline of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>without the leave of the</hi> Chriſtian Magiſtrate, <hi>happily Yee may condemne us as fooles, in that wee hazard thereby our estates and perſons, further then you (which are that way more wiſe)</hi> thinke neceſſary: <hi>but of any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or ſinne therein Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt God, with what Conſcience can you accuſe us, when your owne poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are, that the things wee obſerve, ſhould every of them bee dearer unto us then</hi> 10000 <hi>lives? that they are the peremptory Commandements of God; that no mortall man can diſpence with them, &amp; that the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate greivouſly ſinneth, in constraining thereunto; Will Yee blame any man for doing that of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, which all men ſhould be compelled vnto, which are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93699:4"/> not willing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves? when God Commandeth, ſhall wee anſwer that wee will obey, if ſo be</hi> Caeſar <hi>will grant us leave? Is Diſcipline an Eccleſiaſticall matter, or a Civill? If an Eccleſiaſticall, it must of neceſſity belong to the duty of the Miniſter. And the Miniſter</hi> (Yee ſay) <hi>holdeth all his Authority of doing whatſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth unto the ſpirituall Charge of the houſe of God, even immediatly from God himſelfe, without dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon any Magiſtrate. Whereupon it followeth as we ſuppoſe, that the hearts of the people being willing to bee under the ſcepter of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>the Miniſter of God, into whoſe hands the</hi> Lord <hi>himſelfe hath put that ſcepter, is without all excuſe, if thereby he guide them not. Nor doe we find that hitherto greatly yee have diſliked thoſe Churches abroad, where the people with directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Godly Ministers, have even againſt the will of their Magistrate, brought in either the doctrine, or diſcipline of</hi> IESVS CHRIST. <hi>For which cauſe wee muſt now thinke the very ſame thing of you which our</hi> SAVIOUR <hi>did ſometimes vtter, concerning falſehearted</hi> Scribes <hi>and</hi> Phariſies, THEY SAY AND DOE NOT. Thus the fooliſh Barrowiſt deriveth his ſchiſme,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.23.</note> by way of concluſion, as to him it ſeemeth, directly and plainly out of your principles. Him, therfore, wee leave to bee ſatiſfied by you from whom he hath ſprung. And if ſuch, by your owne acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be perſons dangerous, although as yet, the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations which they have made are of ſmall and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der growth; the changes likely to enſue within this land, in caſe your deſire ſhould take place, muſt be thought upon.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93699:5"/>3. Firſt, concerning the <hi>ſupreame power</hi> of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, they are no ſmall Prerogatives, which now thereunto belonging, the forme of your diſcipline will reſtraine it to reſigne. Againe, it may juſtly be feared, whether our <hi>Engliſh Nobility,</hi> when the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter came in Tryall, would contentedly ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to bee alwayes at the talye, and to ſtand to the ſentence, of a number of meane perſons, aſſiſted with the preſence of their poore Teacher, a man (as ſometimes it hapeneth) though better able to ſpeake, yet no whit apter to judge, then the reſt, from whom, bee their dealings never ſo abſurd (unleſſe it bee by way of complaint to a Synod) no appeale may bee made unto any one of higher power, in as much as the order of your diſcipline admitteth no ſtanding inequality of Court, no ſpirituall Iudge to have any ordinary ſuperior on Earth, but as many ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacies as there are Pariſhes and ſeverall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Neither is it altogether without cauſe, that ſo many doe feare the overthrow of all Learning, as a threatned ſequell of this your intended diſcipline. For,<note place="margin">Sapien. 6.24.</note> if the <hi>Worlds preſervation depend on the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the wiſe;</hi> and of that ſort the number here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be not likely to waxe overgreat,<note place="margin">Eccle. 26 29.</note> when (that wherewith the ſonne of <hi>Syrack</hi> profeſſeth himſelfe at the heart greived) <hi>men of vnderſtanding are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſo little ſet by:</hi> how ſhould their minds whom the love of ſo precious a Iewell, filled with ſecret Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy, even in regard of the leaſt things, which may
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93699:5"/> ny way hinder the flouriſhing eſtate thereof, chuſe, but miſdoubt leaſt this diſcipline which alwaies you match with divine doctrine, as her naturall and true Siſter, bee found unto all kinds of knowledge a ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother? ſeeing that the greateſt worldly hopes, which are propoſed unto the cheifeſt kinde of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yee ſeeke vtterly to extirpate as weeds; and have grounded your Platforme on ſuch propoſitions, as doe in a ſorte undermine thoſe moſt renowned habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, where through the goodneſſe of Almighty God, all commendable Arts and Sciencies are with exceeding great induſtry hitherto (and ſo may they for ever continue) ſtudied, proceeded in, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. To charge you as purpoſely bent to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of that wherein ſo many of you have attained no ſmall perfection, were injurious; only therefore I wiſh that your ſelves did wel conſider how oppoſite certaine your poſitions are unto the ſtate of <hi>Collegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Societies,</hi> wherein the two <hi>Vniverſities</hi> conſiſt. Thoſe degrees which their Statutes binde them to take, are by your lawes taken away; your ſelves who have ſought them yee ſo excuſe, as that yee would have men to thinke yee Iudge them not allowable, but tolerable only, and to be borne with for ſome helpe which yee finde in them unto the furtherance of your purpoſes, till the corrupt eſtate of the Church may be better reformed. Your Lawes forbidding Eccleſiaſtical perſons vtterly the exerciſe of Civill power, muſts needs deprive the Heads and Maſters in the ſame <hi>Colledges</hi> of all ſuch authority
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93699:6"/> as now they exerciſe either at home, by puniſhing the faults of thoſe, who, not as Children to their Parents by the Law of Nature, but altogether by Civill authority are ſubject unto them, or abroad, by keeping Courts amongſt their Tenants. Your Lawes, makeing permanent inequality amongſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, a thing repugnant to the Word of God, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force thoſe <hi>Colledges,</hi> the <hi>Seniors</hi> whereof are all or any part of them Miniſters, under the government of a Maiſter in the ſame vocation, to chooſe as oft as they meet together a new <hi>Preſident.</hi> For, if ſo yee judge it neceſſary to doe in <hi>Synods,</hi> for the avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of permanent inequality amongſt <hi>Ministers,</hi> the ſame cauſe muſt needs, even in theſe <hi>Collegiate Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,</hi> enforce the like. Except peradventure yee mean to avoyd all ſuch abſurdities by diſſolving thoſe Corporations, and by bringing the <hi>Vniverſities</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the forme of the <hi>Schoole of Geneva.</hi> Which thing men the rather are inclined to looke for, in aſmuch as the Miniſtery, whereinto their Founders with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular providence have by the ſame Statutes appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them neceſſarily to enter at a certaine time,<note place="margin">Humb. moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the L. L. P. 50.</note> your lawes binde them much more neceſſarily to forbear, till ſome pariſh abroad call for them.</p>
            <p>Your opinion concerning the <hi>Law Civill</hi> is, that the knowledge thereof might bee ſpared, as a thing which this Land doth not need, <hi>Profeſsors</hi> in that kinde being ſo few, yee are the bolder to ſpurne at them, and not to diſſemble your minds concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theire removall: in whoſe ſtudyes, although my
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93699:6"/> ſelfe have not much beene converſant, nevertheleſſe, exceeding great cauſe I ſee there is to wiſh, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto more encouragement were given, as well for the ſingular treaſures of Wiſdome therein contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as alſo for the great uſe wee have thereof, both in deciſion of certaine kinds of cauſes, ariſeing day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly within our ſelves, and eſpecially for commerce with Nations abroad, Whereunto that knowledge is moſt requiſite.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The reaſons wherewith yee would perſwade, that <hi>Scripture</hi> is the only rule to frame all our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by, are in every reſpect as effectuall for proofe, that the ſame is the only Law whereby to determine all our <hi>Civill</hi> Controverſies. And then what doth let, but as thoſe men have their deſire, who frankly broach it already, that the worke of <hi>Reformation</hi> will never be perfected till the Law of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> bee received alone; ſo pleaders and Counſellours may bring their bookes of the <hi>Common Law,</hi> and beſtow them as the <hi>Students</hi> of curious and needleſſe Arts did theirs in the <hi>Apostles</hi> time?<note place="margin">Act. 19.19.</note> I leave them to ſcan how farre thoſe words of yours may reach, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in yee declare, that whereas many houſes lye waſte through inordinate ſutes in Law,<note place="margin">Humb. moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on P. 74.</note> 
               <hi>This one thing will ſhew the excellency of Diſcipline for the wealth of the Realme, and quiet of Subjects; that the Church is to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſuch a party who is apparently troubleſome and contentious, and without</hi> REASONABLE CAVSE <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a meere will and ſtomacke doth vex and molest his Brother, and trouble the Country.</hi> For my owne part
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93699:7"/> I doe not ſee, but that it might agree very well with your <hi>Principles,</hi> if your diſcipline were fully plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, even to ſend out your writs of ſurceace unto all <hi>Courts of England</hi> beſides, for the moſt things hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in them. A great deale further I might proceed, and deſcend lower.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But for as much as againſt all theſe and the like difficultyes your anſwer is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Counterp.</hi> 6. <hi>P.</hi> 108.</note> that wee ought to ſearch what things are conſonant to Gods word, not which be moſt for our owne eaſe; and therefore that your diſcipline being (for ſuch is your errour) the abſolute commandement of Almighty God, it muſt bee received, although the world by receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſhould be cleane turned vpſide downe, herein lyeth the greateſt danger of all. For whereas the name of divine Authority is uſed to countenance theſe things which are not the commandements of God, but your owne erronious collections; on him you muſt father whatſoever yee ſhall afterwards be led either to doe, in withſtanding the Adverſaries of your cauſe, or to thinke, in maintenance of your doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and what this may bee God doth know: In ſuch kindes of errours, the minde once imagining it ſelfe to ſeeke execution of Gods will, laboureth forthwith to remove both things and perſons which any way hinder it from takeing place, and in ſuch caſes if any ſtrange or new thing ſeeme requiſite to be done, a ſtrang and new opinion concerning the lawfullneſſe thereof is withall received and broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnder countenance of divine Authority.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93699:7"/>7. One example herein may ſerve for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to ſhew that falſe opinions touching the will of God to have things done are wont to bring forth mighty and violent practiſes againſt the hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of them; and thoſe practiſes new opinions more pernicious then the firſt, yea moſt extreamely oppoſite unto that which the firſt did ſeem to intend, where the people took upon them the Reformation of the Church by caſting out Popiſh ſuperſtition, they having received from their Paſtours a generall inſtruction,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.13.</note> that <hi>whatſoever the heavenly Father hath not planted must be rooted out,</hi> proceeded in ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne places ſo farre, that downe went Oratories and the very Temples of God themſelves. For, as they chanced to take the compaſſe of their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſtricter or larger, ſo their dealings were accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly more or leſſe moderate. Among others,<note place="margin">Anabaptiſts.</note> there ſprung up preſently one kinde of men; with whoſe zeale and forwardneſſe the reſt being compared, were thought to be marvellous cold and dull. Theſe grounding themſelves on rules more generall; that <hi>whatſoever the Law of Chriſt commandeth not, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi> Antichriſt <hi>is the Authour, and whatſoever</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt <hi>or his adherents did in the world the true Profeſſours of Chriſt are to undoe;</hi> and found out many things more then others had done, the extirpation whereof was in their Conceipt as neceſſary as of any thing before removed. Hereupon they ſecretly made their dolefull complaints every where as they went, that albeit the World did begin to profeſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93699:8"/> ſome diſlike of that which was evill in the kingdome of darkneſſe, yet fruits worthy of a true repentance were not ſeene; and that if men did repent as they ought, they muſt endeavour to purge the truth of all manner of evill, to the end there might follow a new World afterward, wherein righteouſnes only ſhould dwell. Private repentance they ſaid muſt appeare by every mans faſhioning his owne life contrary unto the cuſtome and orders of this preſent World, both in greater things and in leſſe. To this purpoſe they had alwayes in their mouthes thoſe great things,<note place="margin">Guy des Bres contre l'erreur des Anabapt. <hi>pag. 4.</hi>
               </note> Charity, Faith, the true Feare of God, the Croſſe, the Mortification of the fleſh. All their exhortations were to ſet light of the things in this World, to count riches and honours vanity, and in token thereof, not only to ſeek neither, but if men were poſſeſſours of both, even to caſt away the one and reſigne the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">pag. 5.</note> that all men might ſee their unfained converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto Chriſt. They were ſollicitours of men to faſts,<note place="margin">pag. 16. pag. 118. pag. 119.</note> to often meditations of heavenly things; and as it were conferences in ſecret with God, by prayers not framed according to the frozen manner of the World: but expreſſing ſuch fervent deſires as might even force God to hearken to them. Where they found men in diet, attire, furniture of houſe, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way obſervers of Civility and decent or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,<note place="margin">pag. 120. pag. 116.</note> ſuch they reproved as being carnally and earthly minded. Every word otherwiſe then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely and ſadly uttered, ſeemed to pierce like a ſword through them.<note place="margin">pag. 124.</note> If any man were pleaſant, their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93699:8"/> manner was preſently with ſighs to repeat theſe words of our Saviour Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>Woe bee to you which now laugh, for you ſhall lament.</hi> So great was their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to be alwayes in trouble, that ſuch as did quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lead their lives, they judged of all other men to be in moſt dangerous caſe. They ſo much affected to croſſe the ordinary cuſtome in every thing,<note place="margin">pag. 117.</note> that when other mens uſe was to put on better attire, they would be ſure to ſhew themſelves openly abroad in worſe, the ordinary names of the dayes in the week they thought it a kind of prophaneneſſe to uſe, and therefore, accuſtomed to make no other diſtinction then by number; the 1, 2, 3, day.</p>
            <p n="8">8. From this they proceed unto publique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. Firſt, Eccleſiaſticall, and then Civill. Touching the former they boldly avouched that themſelves only had the truth.<note place="margin">pag. 40.</note> Which thing upon perill of their lives they would at all times defend; and that ſince the Apoſtles lived, the ſame was never before in all points ſincerely taught. Wherefore that things might be brought againe to that ancient inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity which Ieſus Chriſt by his word requireth, they began to controule the Miniſters of the Goſpell, for attributing ſo much force and vertue unto the ſcriptures of God read; whereas the truth was, that when the word is ſaid, to engender faith in the heart and to convert the ſoule of man, or to work any ſuch ſpirituall divine effect, theſe ſpeeches are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto appliable as it is read or preached, but as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted into us by the power of the Holy Ghoſt, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93699:9"/> the eyes of our underſtanding, and ſo revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the myſteries of God, according to that which <hi>Ieremy</hi> promiſed before ſhould be,<note place="margin">Ier. 31.34.</note> ſaying, <hi>I will put my law in their inward parts, and I will write it in their hearts.</hi> The book of God they notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding for the moſt part ſo admired,<note place="margin">pag, 29.</note> that other diſputation againſt their opinions, then only by allegation of ſcripture, they would not heare,<note place="margin">pag. 27.</note> beſides it they thought no other writings in the World ſhould be ſtudyed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that one of their great Prophets exhorting them to caſt away all reſpects unto humane writings, ſo farre to this motion they condeſcended that as many as had any Bookes, ſave the holy Bible, in their Cuſtody, they brought and ſet them publiquely on fire.</p>
            <p n="9">9. When they and their Bibles were alone to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, what ſtrange fantaſticall opinion ſoever at any time entred into their heads, their uſe was to thinke the ſpirit taught it them. Their frenſies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Saviours Incarnation: the ſtate of ſoules departed and ſuch like, are things needleſſe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed. And foraſmuch as they were of the ſame ſuit with thoſe, of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>They are ſtill learning but never attaining to the knowledge of truth,</hi> it was no marvaile to ſee them every day broach ſome new thing never heard of before, which reſtleſſe levity they did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret to be their growing to ſpirituall perfection, and a proceeding from faith to faith.<note place="margin">pag. 65. pag. 66.</note> The differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among them grew in a manner infinite, ſo that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93699:9"/> ſcarcely was there found any one of them, the forge of whoſe braine was not poſſeſt with ſome ſpeciall myſtery.<note place="margin">pag. 135.</note> Whereupon although their mutuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions were moſt fiercely proſecuted among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet when they came to defend the common cauſe, common to them all againſt the Adverſaries of their factions, they had wayes to lick one another whole, the ſounder in his owne perſwaſion excuſing <hi>The deare Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 25.</note> which were not ſo farre en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, and profeſſing a charitable hope of the mercy of God towards them, notwithſtanding their ſwarving from him in ſome things.<note place="margin">pag. 71.</note> Their owne Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters they highly magnifyed, as men whoſe vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was from God: the reſt,<note place="margin">pag. 124.</note> their manner was diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to terme <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> to accompt their calling an humane creature, and to detaine the people, as much as might be, from hearing of them.<note place="margin">pag. 764.</note> As touching Baptiſme adminiſtred in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they judged to be an execrable mockery, and no Baptiſme, both, becauſe the Miniſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the Papacy are wicked Idolaters, lewd perſons, Theeves and Murderers, curſed creatures, ignorant beaſts; and alſo, that for to baptize is a proper action belonging unto none but the Church of Chriſt, whereas <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Synagogue.<note place="margin">pag. 748.</note> The cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of uſing <hi>God-fathers</hi> and <hi>God-mothers</hi> at Chriſtnings they ſcorned. <hi>Baptizing of Infants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 512.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though confeſt by themſelves to have been continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed even ſithence the very Apoſtles owne times, yet they altogether condemned, partly,<note place="margin">pag. 518.</note> becauſe ſundry
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93699:10"/> errours are of no leſſe antiquity:<note place="margin">pag. 722.</note> and partly becauſe there is no commandement in the Goſpell of Chriſt which ſaith Baptize Infants, but he contrariwiſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Goe preach and Baptize,</hi> doth appoint that the Miniſter of Baptiſme ſhall in that action firſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter doctrine, and then Baptiſme, as alſo in ſaying, <hi>whoſoever doth believe and is Baptized,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 688.</note> he appointeth that the perſon, to whom Baptiſme is adminiſtred, ſhall firſt beleeve, and then be Baptized; to the end that beleeving may goe before this Sacrament in the receiver, no otherwiſe then preaching in the giver, ſith equally in both, the law of Chriſt declareth, not only what things are required, but alſo in what or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they are required.<note place="margin">pag. 38.</note> The <hi>Eucharist</hi> they received (pretending our Lord and Saviours example) after Supper: and for avoyding all thoſe impieties which have beene grounded upon the myſticall words of Chriſt, <hi>This is my body, this is my bloud,</hi> they thought it not ſafe to mention either body or blood in that Sacrament,<note place="margin">pag. 122.</note> but rather to abrogate both, and to uſe no words but theſe, <hi>Take, eat, declare the death of our Lord; Drinke, ſhew forth our Lords death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Rites and Ceremonies their profeſſion was, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of all conformity with the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> for which cauſe they would rather endure any torment, then obſerve the <hi>ſolemne feſtivalls</hi> which others did, in aſmuch as <hi>Antichriſt</hi> (they ſaid) was the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventor of them.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The pretended end of their Civill Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was, that Chriſt might have dominion over all;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93699:10"/> that all Crownes and Scepters might bee throwne downe at his feet; that no other might raigne over Chriſtian men but he; no Regiment keep them in awe but his diſcipline; amongſt them no ſword at all to be carried beſides his, the ſword of Spirituall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication. For this cauſe they laboured with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all their might in overturning the Seates of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, becauſe Chriſt hath ſaid,<note place="margin">pag. 841.</note> 
               <hi>Kings of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> in aboliſhing the execution of Iuſtice, becauſe Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>reſiſt not evill;</hi> in forbidding Oathes the neceſſary meanes of Iudiciall Tryall, becauſe Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Sweare not at all;</hi> finally,<note place="margin">pag. 849.</note> in bringing in community of goods, becauſe Chriſt by his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles hath given the World ſuch example, to the end that men might excell one another, not in wealth, the pillar of ſecular authority, but in vertue.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Theſe men at the firſt were only pittied in their errour, and not much withſtood by any;<note place="margin">pag. 40.</note> the great humility, zeale and devotion, which appeared to bee in them was in all mens opinion a pledge of their harmleſſe meaning. The hardeſt that men of ſound Iudgement conceived of them, was but this,<note place="margin">Lactant.</note> 
               <hi>O quàm honeſtâ voluntate miſeri errant; with how good a meaning theſe poore ſoules doe evill! Luther</hi> made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt unto <hi>Frederick</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> that within his dominion they might be favourably dealt with and ſpared,<note place="margin">Juſt. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> for that (their errour exempted) they ſeemed otherwiſe right good men. By meanes of which mercifull toleration they gathered ſtrength,<note place="margin">pag. 6.</note> much more then was ſafe for the ſtate of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93699:11"/> wherein they lived. They had their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret corner-meetings and aſſemblies in the night, the people flocked unto them by thouſands. The means whereby they both allured and retained ſo great multitudes were moſt effectuall;<note place="margin">Pag. 4. 20.</note> firſt, a wonderfull ſhew of zeale towards God,<note place="margin">Pag. 55.</note> wherewith they ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to bee even rapt in every thing they ſpake. Secondly, an hatred of ſinne and a ſingular love of integrity, which men did thinke to be much more then ordinary in them, by reaſon of the Cuſtome which they had to fill the eares of the people with invectives againſt their authorized Guids, aſwell Spirituall as Civill. Thirdly, the bountyfull releife wherewith they eaſed the broken eſtate of ſuch needy Creatures as were in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the more apt to be drawne away. Fourthly, a tender Compaſſion which they were thought to take upon the miſeries of the Common ſort, over whoſe heads their manner was,<note place="margin">Pag. 6. 7.</note> even to powre downe ſhowrs of teares, complaining that <hi>no reſpect was had unto them,</hi> that <hi>their goods were devoured by wicked Cormorants,</hi> their <hi>perſons had in contempt, all liberty both temporall and ſpirituall taken from them,</hi> that <hi>it was high time for god now to heare their groanes and to ſend them deliverance:</hi> Laſtly, a cunning ſlight which they had to ſtroake and ſmooth up the minds of their followers, as well by appropriating unto them all the favourable Titles, the good words and the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious promiſies in <hi>Scripture;</hi> as alſo by caſting the contrary alwaies on the heads of ſuch as were ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93699:11"/> from that retinue. Whereupon, the <hi>Peoples</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acclamations unto ſuch deceivers was, <hi>Theſe are verely the men of God, theſe are his true and ſincere Prophets.</hi> If any ſuch Prophet or man of God did ſuffer by order of law condigne and deſerved pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, were it for Fellony, Rebellion, Murder or what elſe, the people (ſo ſtrangely were their hearts inchanted) as though bleſſed <hi>Saint Stephen</hi> had bene againe Martyred,<note place="margin">Pag. 27.</note> did lament that God tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his moſt deare ſervants from them.</p>
            <p n="12">12. In all things beeing fully perſwaded, that what they did it was Obedience to the will of God, and that all men ſhould doe the like; there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after ſpeculation, practiſe, whereby the whole world thereunto (if it were poſſible) might be framed.<note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> This they ſaw could not be done without mighty oppoſition and reſiſtance: againſt which to ſtrengthen themſelves, they ſecretly entred into a league of aſſociation. And peradventure, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that although they were many, yet long warrs would in time waſt them out; they began to thinke whether it might not be that God would have them doe for their ſpeedy and mighty increaſe, the ſame which ſometime Gods owne choſen people, the people of <hi>Iſraell</hi> did. Glad and faine they were to have it ſo: which very deſire was it ſelfe apt to breed both an opinion of poſſibility, and a willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to gather arguments of likelyhood that ſo God himſelfe would have it. Nothing more cleare unto their ſeeming, then that <hi>a new Ieruſalem</hi> beeing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93699:12"/> often ſpoken of in <hi>Scripture,</hi> they undoubtedly were themſelves that new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the old did by way of a certaine figurative reſemblance ſignifie what they ſhould bee and doe. Here they drew in a Sea of matter by applying of all things unto their owne company, which are any where ſpoken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning divine favours, and benefits beſtowed upon the old common wealth of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> concluding that as <hi>Iſraell</hi> was delivered out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſo they ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally out of the <hi>Egypt</hi> of this <hi>Worlds</hi> ſervile thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome unto ſinne and ſuperſtition; as <hi>Iſraell</hi> was to root out the Idolatrous Nations, and to plant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of them a people which feared God, ſo the ſame Lords good will and pleaſure was now, that theſe new <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhould under the Conduct of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Ioſhuas, Sampſons,</hi> and <hi>Gideons</hi> performe a worke no leſſe miraculous in caſting out violently the wicked from the earth, and eſtabliſhing the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Chriſt</hi> with perfect liberty: and therefore as the cauſe why the Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> tooke unto one man many wives, might be, leaſt the caſualties of warre ſhould any way hinder the promiſe of God concerning their multitude from takeing effect in them, ſo it was not unlike that for the neceſſary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of <hi>Chriſts</hi> kingdome under the Goſpell, the Lord was content to allow aſmuch. Now what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they did in ſuch ſort collect out of <hi>Scripture,</hi> when they came to juſtifie or perſwade it unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, all was <hi>the heavenly fathers appointment, his commandement, his will and charge.</hi> Which thing is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93699:12"/> the point, in regard whereof I have gathered this declaration. For my purpoſe herein is to ſhew, that when the minds of men are once erroniouſly perſwaded, that it is the will of God to have thoſe things done which they fancy; their opinions are as thornes in their ſides, never ſuffering them to take reſt till they have brought their ſpeculations into practiſe; the reſts &amp; impediments of which practiſe, their reſtleſſe deſire and ſtudy to remove, leadeth them every day forth by the hand into other more dangerous opinions, ſometimes quite and cleane contrary to their firſt pretended meanings; ſo as what will grow out of ſuch errours as goe maſked under the cloake of divine Authority, impoſſible it is that ever the witt of man ſhould imagine, till time have brought forth the fruits of them; for which cauſe it behooveth wiſdome to feare the ſequells thereof, even beyond all apparent cauſe of feare. Theſe men in whoſe mouthes at the firſt ſounded nothing but only mortification of the fleſh, were come at the length to thinke they might lawfully have their ſix or ſeven Wives a peece. They which at the firſt, thought judgement and juſtice it ſelfe a mercyleſſe cruelty; accompted at the length their owne hands ſanctified, with being imbrued in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian</hi> blood; they, who at the firſt were wont to beat downe all dominion and to urge againſt poore <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, Kings of Nations,</hi> had at the length both <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulls</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> of their owne erection; finally, they which could not brooke at the firſt, that any man
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93699:13"/> ſhould ſeek, no not by law, the recovery of goods injuriouſly taken or withheld from him; were growne at the laſt to thinke, they could not offer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God more acceptable ſervice, then by turning their Adverſaries cleane out of houſe and home, and by inriching themſelves with all kind of ſpoyle and pillage,<note place="margin">pag. 41.</note> which thing being layd to their charge, they had in all readineſſe their anſwer, that now the time was come, when according to our Saviours promiſe, <hi>The meeke ones muſt inherit the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.5.</note> and that their title hereunto, was the ſame which the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had unto the goods of the wicked <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 11.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. Wherfore ſith the World hath had in theſe men ſo freſh experience how dangerous ſuch active errours are, it muſt not offend you, though touching the ſequell of your preſent miſperſwaſions much more be doubted, then your owne intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes doe happily ayme at. And yet your words all-ready are ſomewhat, when ye affirme that <hi>your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mart. in his <hi>3.</hi> libel. P. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Elders, Doctours, and Deacons, ought to bee in this Church of</hi> England, <hi>whither his Majeſty and our State will, or no;</hi> when for the animating of your Confederates, yee publiſh the Muſters which yee have made of your owne bands, and proclaime to amount unto, I know not how many thouſands; when yee threaten, that <hi>ſith neither ſuits to the</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>nor ſupplications to our</hi> Convocation-Houſe, <hi>neither your defences by writing, nor challenges of diſputation in behalfe of that cauſe are able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayle,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93699:13"/> wee muſt blame our ſelves, if to bring in diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline ſome ſuch meanes bee uſed hereafter, as ſhall cauſe all our hearts to ake.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Demonſtr. in the Preface.</note> That things doubtfull are to be conſtrued in the better part, is a principle that ought not to be followed in matters concerning the publique ſtate of a Common-wealth. But howſoever theſe and the like ſpeeches be accompted as arrowes idly ſhot at randome, without either eye had to any marke, or regard to their lighting place: hath not your longing deſire for the practiſe of your diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, brought the matter already unto this demur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer amongſt you; whether the people and their godly Paſtours, that way affected, ought not to make ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the reſt, and to begin the exerciſe of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, without the licence of Civill powers, which licence they ſought for, and are not heard? Upon which queſtion, as ye have now divided your ſelves, the warier ſort of you takeing the one part, and the forwarder in zeale the other; ſo in caſe theſe earneſt ones ſhould prevaile? what other ſequell can any wiſe man imagine, but this; that having firſt reſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that attempts for diſcipline without ſuperiours, are lawfull, it will follow in the next place to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted what may bee attempted againſt ſuperiours, which will not have the ſcepter of that diſcipline to rule over them?</p>
            <p n="14">14. Yea even by you, which have ſtayed your ſelves from running headlong with the other ſort, ſomewhat notwithſtanding there hath bene done, without the leave or likeing of your lawfull Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93699:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:93699:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:93699:15"/> for the exerciſe of a part of your diſcipline a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Clergy</hi> thereunto addicted. And leaſt examination of principall parties therein, ſhould bring thoſe things to light, which might hinder and let your proceedings; behold for a barre againſt that impediment, one opinion yee have newly added unto the reſt, even upon this occaſion, an opinion to exempt you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> takeing Oathes; which may turne to the moleſtation of your Brethren in that cauſe. The next neighbour opinion, whereunto when occaſion requireth, may follow for diſpenſation with Oathes already taken, if they afterwards be found to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a neceſſity of detecting ought which may bring ſuch good men into trouble or damage whatſoever the cauſe bee. O mercyfull God! what mans witt is there able to ſound the depth of theſe dangerous and fearfull evills, whereinto our weake and impotent nature is inclinable to ſinke it ſelfe, rather then to ſhew an acknowledgment of errour in that, which once wee have unadviſedly taken upon us to defend, againſt the ſtreame, as it were, of a contrary publique reſolution? Wherefore if wee any thing reſpect their errour, who being perſwaded even as yee are, have gone further upon that perſwation then yee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, if wee regard the preſent eſtate of the <hi>highest Governour</hi> placed over us, if the quality and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of our <hi>Nobles,</hi> if the Orders and Lawes of our famous <hi>Vniverſities,</hi> of the profeſſion of the <hi>Civill</hi> or the practiſe of the <hi>Common-Law</hi> amongſt us, if the miſchieves, whereinto even before our eyes, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93699:15"/> others have fallen headlong from no leſſe plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and faire beginings, then yours are: there is in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of theſe conſiderations moſt juſt cauſe to feare, leaſt our haſtineſſe to imbrace a thing of ſo peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Conſequence, ſhould cauſe poſterity to feele thoſe evills, which as yet are more eaſy for us to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, then they would be for them to remedy.<note place="margin">The Concl. of all.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. The beſt and ſafeſt way therefore for you, my deare Brethren, is, to call your deeds paſt to a new reckoning, to examine the cauſe yee have taken in hand, and to try it even point by point, Argument by Argument, with all the diligent exactneſſe yee can; to lay aſide the Gall of that bitterneſſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your minds have hitherto overabounded, and with meekneſſe to ſearch the Truth; thinke yee are men, deeme it not impoſſible for yee to erre; fift un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially your owne hearts, whether it bee the force of reaſon or vehemency of affection which hath bred and ſtill doth feed theſe opinions in you. If truth doe any where manifeſt it ſelfe, ſeeke not to ſmother it with gloſing deluſion, acknowledge the greatneſſe thereof, and thinke it your beſt victory when the ſame doth prevaile over you.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That yee have bene earneſt in ſpeaking and writing againe and againe the contrary way, ſhall bee no blemiſh nor diſcredit at all unto you. Amongſt ſo many ſo huge volumes as the infinite paines of <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> hath brought forth, what one hath gotten him greater love, commendation, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour then the booke wherein he carefully collecteth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93699:16"/> 
               <hi>his owne overſights,</hi> and ſincerely condemneth them? Many ſpeeches there are of <hi>Iobes,</hi> whereby his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and other vertues may appeare: but the glory of an ingenious mind hee hath purchaſed by theſe words only,<note place="margin">Iob. 39.37.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, I will lay mine hand on my mouth, I have ſpoken once, yet will I not therefore maintaine argument: yea twice, howbeit for that cauſe, further I will not proceede.</hi> Farre more comfort it were for us (ſo ſmall is the joy wee take in theſe ſtrifes) to labour under the ſame yoake, as men that looke after the ſame eternall reward of their labours, to bee injoyed with you in bands of indiſſoluble love and amity, to live as if our perſons being many, our Soules were but one, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſuch diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred ſort, to ſpend our few &amp; wretched dayes in a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious proſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wearyſome contentions, the end whereof, if they have not ſome ſpeedy end will bee heavy even on both ſides. Brought already wee are, even to that eſtate, which <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> mournfully deſcribed, ſaying.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">G. Naz: Apol.</note>
               <hi>My mind leadeth mee (ſith there is no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy) to fly and to convey my ſelfe into ſome corner out of ſight, where I may ſcape from this cloudy tempest of maliciouſneſse, whereby all parts are entred into a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warre amongſt themſelves, and that little remnant of love which was, is now conſumed to nothing. The only godlyneſſe wee glory in, is to find out ſomewhat whereby wee may Iudge others to bee ungodly. Each others faults wee obſerve, as matter of exprobration, and not of greife. By theſe meanes wee are growne
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93699:16"/> hatefull in the eyes of the heathens themſelves, and (which woundeth us the more deeply) able we are not to deny, but that wee have deſerved their hatred. With the better ſort of our owne, our fame and Credit is cleane lost. The leſſe wee are to marvaile, if they Judge vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of us, who although wee did well, would hardly allow thereof. On our backs they alſo build, that are lewd, and what wee object one againſt another, the ſame they uſe to the utter ſcorne and diſgrace of us all. This wee have gained by our mutuall home diſsentions. This wee are worthyly rewarded with, which are more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſtrive, then becometh men of vertuous and mild diſpoſition.</hi> But our truſt with the almighty is, that with us, contentions are now at their, higheſt floate, and that the day will come (for what cauſe of diſpaire is there,) when the paſſions of former enmity being allayed, wee ſhall with ten times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled tokens of our unfainedly reconciled love, ſhew our ſelves each towards other the ſame, which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and the <hi>Brethren</hi> of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> were at the time of their intervew in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Our comfortable expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and moſt Thirſty deſire whereof, what man ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever amongſt you ſhall any wayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (as wee truely hope there is no one amongſt you but ſome way or other will) the bleſſing of the God of peace, both in this world, and in the world to come, be upon him, more then the ſtarres of the firmament in number. AMEN.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93699:17"/>
               <head>ECCLES. POLIT. <hi>LIB.</hi> 5. §. 79. ad fin.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>uch is the generall deteſtation of rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing God or the church; that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as nothing doth either in peace or warre more uphold mens reputation then proſperous ſucceſſe, becauſe, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſtruction, unleſſe notorious improbitie bee joyned with proſperity, it ſeemeth to argue favour with God, they which once have ſtained their hands with theſe odious ſpoiles, doe thereby faſten unto all their actions an eternall preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; in reſpect whereof, for that it paſſeth through the world as an undoubted rule and principle, that ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege is open defiance to god, whatſoever afterward they vndertake, if they proſper in it, men reckon it but <hi>Dionyſius</hi> his navigation, and if any thing befall them otherwiſe, it is not, as commonly, ſo in them aſcribed to the great uncertainty of caſuall events, wherein the providence of God doth controle the purpoſes of men, oftentimes much more for their good, then if all things did anſwere fully their hearts deſire, but the cenſure of the world is ever directly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93699:17"/> againſt them, both<note n="a" place="margin">Novimus multa regna &amp; reges eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum propterea cecidiſſe, quia Eccleſias ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaverunt, reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> earum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaverunt, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enaverunt vel diripuerunt; Epiſcopiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; ſacer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otibus, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>que quod majus eſt, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiis eorum abſtulerunt, &amp; pugnantibus dederunt. Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propter nec fortes in bello, nec in fide ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles fuerunt, nec victores extiterunt, ſed terga multi vulnerati, &amp; plures inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecti verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, regnáque &amp; regiones, &amp; quod pejus eſt, regna coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtia perdide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, atque propriis haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatibus ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruerunt, &amp; hactenus ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. verba Caroli Mag. in Capital. Caral. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>104.</hi>
                  </note> bitter and peremptory.</p>
               <p>To make ſuch actions therefore leſſe odious, and to mitigate the envy of them, many colourable ſhifts and inventions have beene uſed, as if the world did hate only wolves, and thinke the fox a godly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The time<note n="b" place="margin">Turno tempus erit magno cùm optaverit emptum. Intactum Pallanta, &amp; cùm spolia iſta, diem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Oderit. virgil Aeen. lib. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> it may bee will come, when they that either violently have ſpoiled, or thus ſmoothly defrauded God, ſhall finde they did but deceive themſelves. In the meane while, there will bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſome ſkilfull perſons, which can teach a way how to grind treatably the Church, with jawes that ſhall ſcarce move, and yet devoure in the end more then they that come ravening with open mouth, as if they would worrie the whole man inſtant. Others alſo who have waſtfully eaten out their owne patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, would be glad to repaire if they might their decayed eſtates, with the ruine they care not of what, nor of whom, ſo the ſpoiles were theirs; whereof in ſome part if they happen to ſpeede, yet commonly they are men borne under that conſtellation, which maketh them, I know not how, as vnapt to enrich themſelves as they are ready to impoveriſh others; it is rheir lot to ſuſtaine during life, both the miſery of beggars, and infamy of robbers.</p>
               <p>But though no other plague and revenge ſhould follow ſacrilegious violations of holy things, the naturall diſgrace and ignominy, the very turpitude of ſuch actions in the eyes of a wiſe vnderſtanding
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93699:18"/> heart, is it ſelfe<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Demoſt. Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam non dico legum, quas ſaepe pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punt; ſed ipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us turpitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis quae acer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſima eſt, non vident. Cic. Off. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punita credi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eſſe quae inviſo ſunt, aut ùllum ſupplicium gravius exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imas publico odio? Senec de Benef. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> a heavy puniſhment. Men of vertuous quality, are by this ſufficiently moved to beware, how they anſwer and require the mercyes of God with injuries, whether openly or indirectly offered.</p>
               <p>By meanes whereof the church moſt commonly for gold hath flanell, and whereas the uſuall ſaw of old was, <hi>Glaucus his changeing,</hi> the proverbe is now, <hi>A Church bargaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for feare leſt covetouſneſſe alone ſhould linger out the time too much, and not bee able to make ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocke of the houſe of God, with that expedition which the mortall enemy thereof did vehemently wiſh, he hath by certaine ſtrong inchauntments, ſo deeply bewitcht religion it ſelfe, as to make it in the end an earneſt ſollicitor. and an eloquent perſwader of ſacrilege, urging confidently, that the very beſt ſervice which men of power can doe to Chriſt, is without any more ceremony,<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ventum videtur (quod non ſiue gemitu dixeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>) ut magna hominum pars credat ſeſe tùm demum verè regnum Antichriſti evafiſſe, fi sum bonis Eccleſiae ludant pro libitu.</hi> Calvin. <hi>Ep.</hi> 33. <hi>vide etiam ep.</hi> 13.65.68.108. <hi>vbi de hac ſacrilegà diſſipatione queritur.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In the time of Popery, the Church of <hi>Geneva</hi> was very richly endowed with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venewes. At the reformation, <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Farell</hi> called upon the magiſtrates, as they would anſwer it to God, to imploy all that holy ſtock only to pious and holy uſes, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureing them they could not any other wayes beſtow any part of it, without the guilt of horrible Sacrilege. (So it is a degree of Sacrilege, any way to alter the wills and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of founders, ſo far as they are tolerable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They promiſed fairely; but haveing poſſeſſed themſelves of the goods and patrimony of the Clergy, they ſet apart ſome ſmall portions for the Univerſity, and the miniſters, beſtowing the reſt in fortifieing their walls, and furniſhing their magazine againſt the Biſhop (the lord and owner of the towne) and other more baſe uſes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Calvin</hi> ſeeing this Sacrilege, and deteſting it, was wont to ſay with great griefe, <hi>I ſee wee have taken the purſe from Judas, and given it to the Divell.</hi> Severall men of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit have heard this related by a grave learned French miniſter yet liveing (or very lately) in England.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to ſweepe all,</hi> and to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93699:18"/> leave the Church as bare, as in the day it was firſt borne; that fulneſſe of bread having made the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the houſehould wanton, it is without any ſcruple to be taken away from them, and throwne to doggs; that they which layd the prices of their lands, as offerings at the Apoſtles feet, did but ſow the ſeeds of ſuperſtition; that they which did endow Churches with lands, poyſoned religion; that Tithes and oblations are now in the ſight of God as the ſacrificed bloud of goates, that if wee give him our hearts, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, our goods are better beſtowed otherwiſe; that <hi>Irenaeus, Policarps</hi> diſciple, ſhould not have ſaid, <hi>wee offer unto God our goods, as tokens of thankfullneſſe for what wee doe receive;</hi> neither <hi>Origen, hee that worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth God, must by guifts and oblations acknowledge him the Lord of all;</hi> in a word, that to give unto God is error, reformation of error, to take from the Church, that which the blindneſſe of former ages did unwiſely give. By theſe or the like ſuggeſtions received with all joy; and with like ſedulity practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in certaine parts of the Chriſtian world, they have brought to paſſe, that as <hi>David</hi> doth ſay of man, ſo it is in hazard to bee verified concerning the whole religion and ſervice of God; <hi>The time thereof may peradventure fall out to be threeſcore &amp; ten years, or if ſtrength doe ſerve, unto fourſcore, what followeth, is like to be ſmall joy for them, whatſoever they be that behold it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:93699:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Thus have the beſt things beene overthrowne not ſo much by puiſſance, and might of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, as through defect of counſell in them, that ſhould have upheld and defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93699:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
